<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>XML, blockchain and regulatory reporting in the world of finance</title>
        <subtitle>Combining the strengths and weaknesses of mature and modern technologies to drive innovation and regulatory compliance</subtitle>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Lech</firstname>
                <surname>Rzedzicki</surname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        <abstract>
            <para>The regulatory burden for financial institutions makes it a hard environment to innovate, yet the unfavourable market conditions mean that banks must adopt latest technologies to cut costs and keep up with the market demands.</para>
            <para>This paper aims to show a technical proof of concept of how to combine the seemingly opposite goals using a combination of tried and tested XML technologies such as XSLT and Schematron in conjunction with experimental distributed ledged technology to drive both regulatory compliance and implement innovative features such as inter-bank trade settlemnt using blockchain technology. </para>
            
        </abstract>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Background</title>
        <section>
            <title>XML in regulatory reporting</title>
            <para>XML 1.0 is by now a very mature standard. As most of the audience will know, the standard hasn't changed in 20 years. XML 1.1 hasn't been widely adopted and no one is contemplating XML 2.0 to replace XML 1.0 anytime soon.</para>
            <para>The strenght of that is stability, great tool support, human readability and the reach.</para>
            <para>This means XML still is, probably more than before, a good archival and reporting markup. Worst case scenario is someone will open it in 20 years time in a text editor and it will still be readable.</para>
            <para>Enter the magical world of finance where common sense quickly disappears and is
                replaced by exotic, derivative products such as index variance swaps, whose main
                goal is to depart the client from their money.</para>
            <para>It is hard to prove whether the complex financial product were engineered as a way
                to improve the bottom line of financial institutions or are they truly filling a
                market need for the clients such as shielding them from volatility of the equities
                markets or commodity prices.</para>
            <para>What is universally true however is that the products are complex and it is often hard to figure out who is exposed to risks and to what extent.</para>
            <para>As a result various regulatory bodies, such as the FCA have started requiring more and more reporting on the trades, positions and risks.</para>
            <para>As it happens XML is a great fit for this purpose and XML (and more specifically XML standard called FpML) has been a de facto standard for regulatory reporting to the extent that the regulatory bodies require that the reporting be done in XML</para>
            <para>Regulatory reporting is one of the major considerations and driving forces for any established or upcoming financial organisations in 2016.</para>
            
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Fintech innovation and blockchain</title>
            <para>Another trend in 2016 is the need to radically disrupt or reinvent and optimise financial services institutions.</para>
            <para>Even armed with a full suite of exotic financial products and masses of individual and institutional clients, in an era of negative interest rates and fierce competition from non-traditional players such as supermarkets and tech companies, financial institutions find that a combination of low yields and high regulatory costs make it impossible to retain status quo and still provide sufficient returns back to clients and shareholders.</para>
            <para>Executives in financial institutions are desperately looking for solutions and for many they have found the holy grail by the name of blockchain.</para>
            <para>Originally devised by the mysterious Satoshi Nakamoto for the purposes of using with bitcoin, the concept of a distributed ledger is a powerful one.</para>
            <para>Blockchain or distributed ledger uses solid and well known cryptography around factoring large prime numbers to make it hard to calculate and verify transactions on the ledger and mathematically nearly impossible to alter them by any single contributor.</para>
            <para>By now the technology has enjoyed a massive wave of early adopter hype and
                financial institution have been heavenly looking at using it for trade settlement
                and smart contracts.</para>
            <para>A single project called r3cev alone has gathered over 40 international financial
                institutions and has recently completed the early tests with 11 of them.</para>
            <para>it is therefore an excellent example of an innovative technology that many financial institutions would like to try and we will be using it in the paper to showcase how innovation, XML and regulatory reporting can play together nicely.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Distributed ledgers history</title>
            <para>Ledgers have been used throughout human history, from Sumerian records of harvests and crop usage 4500 years ago through to the tracking of bad debts by the Medici bank in the 14th and 15th Century. Today’s modern double-entry ledgers can trace their roots back to early Islamic records in 7th Century and were first publicly codified in Venice in 1494 by Friar Luca Pacioli based on the practice of Venetian merchants of the Renaissance.  Distributed ledgers represent the next evolution of these devices.</para>
            
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What is a distributed ledger?</title>
            <para>A distributed ledger is essentially an asset database that can be shared across a network of multiple sites, geographies or institutions. All participants within a network can have their own identical copy of the ledger and any changes to the ledger are reflected in all copies in minutes, or in some cases, seconds.  The security and accuracy of the assets stored in the ledger are maintained cryptographically through the use of ‘keys’ and signatures to control who can do what within the shared ledger. Entries can also be updated by one, some or all of the participants, according to rules agreed by the network.</para>
            <para>It is important to understand that typically the design is such that you can only add new entries to the ledger and can not remove previous entries. If you wish to amend entries, you add a new, cerrected entry and a reference the old one.
            </para>
            <para>This also means that the ledger, whether it is stored as a file or in a database, will grow over time which is both a strength and a weakness. t makes it almost impossible to falsify previously added information, but it also makes it hard when you truly need to change the information – a person changes name, or there was any other factual error when entering the information on the blockchain.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What can you use distributed ledgers for?</title>
            <para>There are three core use cases where distributed ledgers can be used:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>Distributed ledgers can be used to secure an enormous range and type of value transactions – from simple money transfers, of which bitcoin provides the best exemplar, to complex registration of asset ownership and transfer such as in the financial services industry.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Distributed ledgers can be used to provably convey trust between parties and verify provenance, reputation or competence – certification of university qualifications, the status of components within a complex supply chain such as an aircraft engine manufacture.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Distributed ledger can serve as the backend execution environment, a distributed "computer in the cloud", where algorithms are executed on the blockchain rather than on any particular machine.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>There is also a number of areas where people see blockchain as the holy grail and mistakenly think it can be applied to anything from preventing diamond forgeries to solving blood bank reserves inefficiencies.</para>
            <para>As a general rule, whenever there is a part of the system that can not be put <quote>on the blockchain</quote>, for example physical assets, or 3rd party IT systems, a blockchain solution is unlikely to work as information can be changed easily outside the blockchain.</para>
            
        </section>
        <section><title>Blockchain challenges</title>
            <para>There are currently a number of fundamental challenges with blockchain based distributed ledgers, particularly around scalability and privacy of information on a public blockchain (many of these are resolved in a private blockchain systems).</para>
            <para>The <emphasis>scalability challenges</emphasis> are numerous - the transaction limits for blockchain based systems are low (20 per second for Ethereum, a common next generation blockchain system), the energy requirement for proof of work based consensus systems is huge (the Bitcoin network is estimated to use as much energy as the republic of Ireland), although distributed amongst many parties, the requirement for each node to hold a copy of the full ledger means the cost of storing data on the blockchain is computationally high (although this is mitigated by other distributed storage systems such as IPFS).</para>
            <para><emphasis>Privacy challenges</emphasis> exist as a result of each node holding a copy of the ledger – all transactions are visible to all parties currently unless encryption is used on the data.  The immutability of the blockchain also raises a potential legislative challenge around the European “right to be forgotten”.  How do you erase records on the blockchain?</para>
            <para>Due to the above concerns, usually the blockchain stores just a hash – a signature
                of the transaction or information and the private information is stored separately
                in a wallet and protected by a private key. This is turn means that if a private key
                is lost, it makes it impossible to verify any previous or future information for
                that key.</para>
            <para>Distributed ledger can only be used to verify the information on the blockchain.
                If the data is falsified or tampered with before or outside of blockchain, a
                distributed ledger can only verify that the data is not on the ledger. An example
                here is diamonds and Everledger. Everledger takes several measurements of the
                diamonds (the way it is cut, the colour, size etc) and puts on the distributed
                ledger. If the diamond is lost or stolen and surfaces ever again, it can be easily
                identified by taking the measurements again and comparing the database stored on the
                distributed ledger. This parallel verifiable digital certification on the blockchain
                can assure buyers and sellers of the provenance of the item.</para>
            <para>Unfortunately, all it takes for a savvy thief to avoid this is to change the
                qualities of the diamond slightly – in the process the diamond might lose some
                value, but it is very likely that a thief will prefer that to getting caught. To sum
                up and generalise this issue, any inputs or outputs that are not on the blockchain
                are vulnerable hence the movement to smart contracts and trying to do as much as
                possible inside the blockchain.</para>
            <para>More research and good education for decision makers is key here – this will
                prevent using blockchain where it is not appropriate – for example where data
                changes often, or high performance or efficiency is required. Many of these
                difficulties are the subject of active research projects, and in the UK EPSRC are
                launching a call this summer to support the research further with up to 10 small
                scale project grants with a total of £3M.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The opportunity for distributed ledgers</title>
            <para>Despite all the identified challenges, the opportunities for distributed ledgers
                are potentially huge. Systems such as Ethereum, Eris, NXT, R3CEV, with integrated
                smart contracts offer the ability to place complex business logic on a public or
                private system where they can be triggered by transactions – contract signing,
                approval of work, external events etc.</para>
            <para>The most direct beneficiary of distributed ledgers technologies are the platform
                developers (initially developing the private blockchain solutions) and the
                application developers. In common with many open source companies, the platform
                business model is to sell proprietary value around an open source core. One
                analogous example is Red Hat – a linux distribution provider that offers their core
                product free of charge and then offers consultancy, integration and development
                services to enterprises – recently they were valued at $2B.</para>
            <para>Assuming there is large scale adoption, application developers stand to create
                value in the same way that the app ecosystem has developed on the Apple and Android
                mobile platforms.</para>
            <para>Distributed ledgers allow for complex business processes between parties who do
                not implicitly trust each other to be automated and hence significant cost savings
                to be achieved in many sectors. The classic example is financial instrument trade
                reconciliation but supply chain is another commonly talked about use case. In many
                of the use cases, the core focus is about cost reduction through the removal of
                unwanted middlemen or through the reduction of duplicated effort across untrusted
                parties. Distributed ledgers may also improve transparency and efficiency, by
                ensuring that regulators and other third parties have full, real time views of
                transactions.</para>
<section>
    <title>Smart contracts and Distributed Autonomous Organisations</title>
    <para>Smart contracts are beyond the scope of this short presentation, but many in the world of blockchain speak about distributed autonomous organisations (DAO), written in code and deployed on the blockchain these lend themselves strongly to new business structures or digitisation of e.g. cooperatives.  How these will develop is unknown at this point, but initial DAO’s have raised millions of pounds in blockchain crowdsales.</para>
                <para>An example of that is Ethereum, where any computation cost can be covered by
                    spending a virtual currency – Ether. Software developers wishing to execute
                    their programs on Ethereum network can choose to outright buy the Ether
                    computing units or provide the computational resources themselves and even sell
                    the excess power in exchange for Ether/money. Such an infrastructure is somewhat
                    similar to cloud services provided by Amazon or Google, where the price is set
                    by the factors such as electricity costs and demand, but with distributed
                    ledger, it is much more fair to smaller players and there is no single entity
                    that can control the network and switch off an application.</para>
                <para>The existence of such networks enables the execution of "Smart Contracts" -
                    autonomous code running on the blockchain (as opposed to a single machine).
                    Given certain conditions, the code can execute automatically. </para>
                <para>A simple example here is bond coupon payment – in a typical bond issue, the
                    buyers buy the bond for 100% of the price and the issuer repay the bond in
                    instalments.</para>
                <para>Traditionally this involves issuing paper certificates of bond ownership and
                    manually sending money via cheque or bank transfer every month and keeping track
                    of what's been repaid etc. Assuming that all the participants – bond issuer and
                    the buyers are also participating in the same distributed ledger network that is
                    capable of executing smart contracts and sending virtual currency, the process
                    can be simplified vastly, possibly even removing the need for intermediaries
                    such as banks (for sending money) and law firms (for writing up the contracts).
                    In such a scenario a bond issuer, would issue a smart contract to be viewed,
                    audited, verified and accepted by the buyers and upon accepting, the funds would
                    be automatically transferred to the issuer. Likewise every instalment the issuer
                    would automatically pay back the coupon payments.</para>
                <para>Smart contracts can enable a whole range of scenarios, from distributing aid
                    money, through voting, secure communications and probably a number of areas that
                    have not been discovered yet. Still the challenges described above
                    remain.</para>
                <para>The successful exploitation of smart contracts requires solving the technical
                    challenges, but also changing laws and regulation and ensuring that the
                    disruption caused by the automation has a net positive effect on societies and
                    the economy.</para>

</section>
        </section>
   

    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Escape velocity for financial institutions</title>
        <para>To many inside and outside the finance industry, the suffocating combination of a low yielding market and the burden of regulatory reporting may feel like a fatality combo from Mortal Combat.</para>
        <para>It isn't and like many combos in fighting games it can be blocked or better yet countered.</para>
        <para>What this paper describes is a proof of concept technical solution to solve two seemingly opposite problems - use tried and tested XML technologies to solve compliance issues for financial institutions while at the same time allow for innovative technologies such as distributed ledger to be used alongside.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Thesis</title>
            <para>XML is a very mature and stable standard. It has built a great ecosystem of technologies that enable financial institutions to reliably solve their regulatory reporting requirements.</para>
            <para>XML does allow mixing in with modern ideas such as distributed ledger or modern
                DevOps stacks such as Docker and modern noSQL solutions such as Marklogic and in
                fact makes it easy to do so, thanks to a few surrounding standards such as XPath,
                XSLT, Xquery or Schematron.</para>
            <para>The aim of this presentation is to show that XML is a great fit for financial
                institutions to deliver both the business as usual activities such as regulatory
                reporting and to explore new areas such as distributed ledger at the same
                time.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Technical Description</title>
        <para>This section describes a sample journey of a financial transaction - a client requests
            FX swap between a client and a bank, the bank executes the transaction, which is then
            published to the distributed ledger and the authenticity is jointly verified on the
            distributed ledger by the client, bank and the regulatory body.</para>
        <para>To best illustrate this, there are three separate instances running blockchain - one
            for the client, one for the bank and one for an imaginary regulatory body called the
            Fictional Compliance Authority.</para>
        <para>We aim to show how to add a transaction, how to sign it, add it to the blockchain, how
            to prove the authenticity of a given transaction, how to run a few basic tests for the
            correctness of the message (using Schematron), what happens when a bank or a rogue party
            tries to falsify data on a blockchain and finally showcase a few good use case where XML
            technologies show their strengths - transforming from raw CSV input to FpML,
            transforming from FpML to a hash and plain text ledger, generating reports and
            graphs.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Infrastructure</title>
            <para>Financial institutions have stringent requirements about robustness of the
                infrastructure. As result they often go for the tried and tested technology as
                opposed to the cutting edge. Our early proof of concept was a setup of Docker
                containers running Python code + open source database. None of that proved to be a
                good fit and the following setup more accurately depicts the needs and wants of the
                IT managers at the financial institutions that we talked to:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>Operating System: Digital Ocean Virtual Machines running CentOS 7 Linux. No special
                        requirements here, as long as the Operating System is capable or running
                        Java. </para>
                    <para>Possible environments where this proof of concept can run (with slight
                        modifications) are: raw Linux Debian or Ubuntu, Linux on top of Docker,
                        Amazon AWS, Azure etc.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Blockchain and "glue" code - Java on Java Runtime Environment 8. We opted for Oracle as this
                        caused least amount of problems and mimics the bank environments that we
                        know of. We are not using any specific version 8 features so this could be
                        downgraded to version 6. As discussed earlier implementation for other
                        platforms and languages are possible - for example, we have started our
                        proof of concept using Python and most of Bitcoin code is written in C. </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Marklogic 8. It is being described as the enterprise noSQL database, has excellent XML
                        technologies support, has replication features that we needed to implement
                        anyway. Having said that, is it possible to use another data persistence
                        mechanism, with additional work.</para></listitem>
                
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>We chose to run three nodes: chain1.kode1100.com, chain2.kode1100.com and
                chain3.kode1100.com to represent three types of institutions - someone initiating a
                transaction (the client), someone facilitating, executing, and reporting the
                transaction (the bank), and an independent regulatory body which we called FCA
                (Fictional Compliance Authority).</para>
            <para>To simplify these will be referred to as node 1-3 or client, bank and FCA
                respectively.</para>
            <para>The minimum setup is a single node and there is no theoretical limit to the
                maximum amount of nodes, although some steps, such as reaching consensus within the
                network will take longer as the network size increases.</para>
            <para>To accurately mimic a realistic setup that could actually reliably work in
                production for a major financial institution, we have configured a high availability
                MarkLogic cluster, where both the configuration, transactional data and the
                blockchain itself are protected from failures using Marklogic enterprise features
                such as clustering and automatic failovers.</para>
            <para>In addition to that, it possible and very easy to configure additional, automatic
                cluster replication, to ensure additional availability in different data centres or
                different time zones.</para>
        </section>
        <section><title>The Stone Circle algorithm</title>
            <para>Kode1100 blockchain proof of concept uses internally developed algorithm called <emphasis>The Stone Circle</emphasis> for generating hashes, new block in the blockchain and verifying hte authenticity of the messages.</para>
            <para><emphasis>The Stone Circle</emphasis> algorithm is a proprietary private consensus algorithm that helps prove a node is in fact one of the trusted delegate node such that it helps prevent man in the middle attacks</para>
        <para>The basic cryptography is based on the original bitcoin protocol (as described in the Bitcoin research paper by Satoshi Nakamoto) with a number of adjustments and improvements. That basic cryptography is using well understood and widely used elliptical curve mathematics and prime number factoring to make any attempts at forging mathematically impossible using current computer technology.</para>
        <para>The improvement in the algorithm, include but are not limited to the following:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>Adjustable difficulty of the hashing function strength. In bitcoin and pretty much all blockchain solutions to date, the security and immutability of the blockchain signature comes with a significant computational cost of having to run hashing functions multiple times (and often discard the results due to race conditions)</para>
                    <para>The stone circle algorithm allows using different hashing implementations,
                        for example SHA-256 instead of SHA-512 to effectively double the performance
                        and slash in half the resource usage for signing the messages. This still
                        results in more than sufficient security of the blockchain due to the
                        multiplication effects of adding more transactions.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Ability to disable coin mining. In a private blockchain setup it is unnecessary to reward
                        participants for signing the messages. In this particular example it is
                        simply a regulatory requirement.</para>
                    <para>By removing the coin mining parts, we are again massively reducing
                        computational waste of calculating who gets the reward and the waste of
                        discarding any computations of those who don't get the reward.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Using ethnographic research to avoid typical human biases against entropy.</para>
                    <para>Using tested and proven </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist></section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Sample operations</title>
        <section>
            <title>Adding a new transaction</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Verifying the business rules of a transaction</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Verifying the hash for a given file</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Summary and the future</title>
        <para>We have showed that XML is still a good fit for business as usual activities such as
            trade onboarding and trade reporting. We also showed how strengths of the XML ecosystem
            can work together with new and emerging technologies, using distributed ledger as an
            example.</para>
        <para>The future steps in this area will largely be market driven, possible next steps
            include open sourcing some or all of the blockchain code for the community to use and
            evolving the blockchain code to enable distributed,verifiable code execution. Such a
            development would then allow applications such as smart contracts and autonomous
            distributed organisations, which are a bit beyond the scope of this presentation, but we
            are more than happy to discuss them.</para>
    </section>
</article>
